Finding aid for Salvador Araneta papers, 1921-1972
Bentley Historical Library
Salvador Araneta papers
1921-1972
Bentley Historical Library
Araneta, Salvador.
87490 Aa microcopy, Aa1
2 microfilms
1 folder
Philippines public servant, delegate to the 1934 and 1972 constitutional conventions. Articles, speeches, and scrapbook; include materials relating to convention activities.
The collection was made available to the California State University Archives for microfilming by Salvador Araneta.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Salvador Araneta was a Philippines lawyer and public servant. He was a delegate to both the 1934 and 1972 constitutional convention.
The Salvador Araneta papers consist mainly of materials relating to his participation as a delegate to the Philippine Constitutional Convention, 1971-1972. Also included are various articles and speeches he made in the period of 1921 to 1955.
Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Scrapbooks.
- Career papers
  - Philippine Constitutional Convention, 1971-1972
    - Resolutions filed by Araneta (Reel 1)
    - Speeches delivered by Araneta (Reel 1)
    - Proposed Amendments made by Araneta to the Committee Reports (Reel 1)
  - Articles and speeches
    - Agricultural and economic subjects (Reel 1)
    - 1921-1935 (Reel 1)
      (most relate to the economic future of the Philippine Islands, the Hare-Hawes-Cutting Act controversy in the Philippines, and the problems of independence from the United States)
    - 1934-1938 (Reel 1)
      (most relate to the first constitutional convention in which Salvador Araneta was a delegate, United States trade relations with the Philippines, and future relations with the United States after independence)
    - 1935-1941 (Reel 1)
      (most relate to the economic consequences of independence, the reexamination of the independence question, and the first constitutional convention)
    - 1946-1955 (Reel 1)
      (speeches)
      (most relate to economic nationalism in the postwar era)
    - Transcript of radio program "Gregorio Araneta Memorial Roundtable Conference", 1970 (Reel 1)
      (series of spontaneous and unrehearsed broadcasts held on the eve of the Constitutional Convention)
    - Transcript of radio program "Gregorio Araneta Memorial Roundtable Conference" (cont.), 1970 (Reel 2)
  - Scrapbook (miscellaneous) (Reel 2)
  - Scrapbook of the Constitutional Convention, February 1970-September 1972 (Reel 2)
  - Segunda Interview Con El Presidente Quezon Pos S. Araneta, 1939 (Folder 1)
    (Transcription of a document that was mistakenly left out of the microfilm edition.)